Yoolim: We have a lot of different ways to
classify all sorts of things in the world.
Chemists, for example, have a table
of elements that sorts the different
elements according to specific
properties, and biologists have a way
to classify all the different species
of animals based on shared traits.
With these classifications, we can
work out key phenomena in biological
evolution or make predictions on how
these different chemicals might react.
We can even consider something
as everyday as a deck of cards.
Each card is classified according
to number, color, and suit or road
signs, which can also be organized
according to a neat scheme.
Even Pokemon have a way
of being classified.
We can use different traits and skills
to determine how they might fare
and battle against other Pokemon.
So whether we realize it or not, most
of the things that we know and enjoy,
or perhaps even take for granted, have
been organized in an orderly way for us.
But one thing that has yet to be
classified in such a way and is quite
crucial to our day-to-day life is letters.
Good classifications are useful
to us because they tell us
something about the world.
The periodic table tells us about the
internal structure of chemicals elements.
The classification of different species
tells us about biological origins,
something as graphic or visual like
road signs or deck of cards can tell
us about how different symbols can
combine to create meaning. Just as well
we have a lot of different scripts that
use a lot of different shapes, but we
haven't quite worked out how letters
are generated using these diverse
shapes with such a classification.
We can work out and begin
to understand this question.
My name is Yoolim Kim and I'm
a researcher at the Max Planck
Institute for the science of human
history here in Jena Germany.
And I'm a part of the Minds and
Traditions research group, which works
on understanding graphic communication.
And one of our key research programs
is understanding and quantifying the
visual properties of letter shapes.
Olivier: Our research group studies
how people use images to communicate.
We study all sorts of graphic
codes from coin designs to
pictographs, to of course writing.
One way to look at writing
systems is to see them as codes
that associate sounds with images,
that is with letters, and letter
shapes is what this project is about.
Looking at most letters, you can
see that they are composed of a
number of smaller, basic shapes.
The inventors of visual symbols
used these basic shapes like
lego blocks, combining them to
create new and distinct shapes.
That is the way that most
writing systems work.
And you can see that for instance,
in the Latin alphabet, the one that's
used to write German or English or
Vietnamese. Think about the tiny arch
in N, it is also repeated in H and in M.
Each script behaves differently.
Some will have fewer building blocks
while others will have far a more
extensive repertoire of basic shapes.
Those with fewer building blocks
can use recombination to create
new and distinctive letters shapes.
Those that have far more building blocks
don't need to use recombination that much.
Some may use some individual
components only once or twice
within the whole system.
As a result of these differences
some scripts will have very
distinctive letters and others won't.
See these two scripts: letter shapes
in this writing system seem less
diverse than the letters in that one.
If you try to imagine what the
next letter in this first strip
might be like, it isn't that hard.
See, not surprising.
These letters are predictable.
They combine a small range of
shapes in a rather regular way.
Not so much for the other script.
That letter shape was hard to
predict just by looking at the rest.
We start from intuitions like this,
but we want to go much further.
Our attempt is to measure the
distinctiveness of letters in
the world's writing systems.
And we define distinctiveness
as the optimal exploration of
the space of possible shapes.
Yoolim: We look at written letters
as if they're just combinations
of smaller building blocks.
Once we know the building blocks of a
writing system and how they combined, we
can begin to imagine letters that don't
quite exist in the system, but have the
potential to do so because they use the
same building blocks as actual letters
and combine according to the same rules.
We call this a space of possible letter
shapes. With this information, we can
begin to work out to what extent scripts
are making efficient use of their
building blocks to generate letters that
are numerous, but also – importantly – as
distinct from one another as possible.
So how are we doing this?
We've built a browser based application
called Glyph, which invites users
to play a simple and fun game with
all sorts of different scripts.
The game is built on a simple
premise that unfolds in two parts.
The premise is that players are presented
with all the letters of the script and
asked to select characters according to
a description or a rule of their choice.
As an example, let's imagine all the
letters of the Greek alphabet. In the
first part we look to see how we can
select characters according to whether or
not they share a certain characteristic.
Looking at the letters
I can see that many of
them have rounded edges.
I select the characters that do
and provide a brief description of
the rule, motivating my selection.
It's important that we select characters
in a way that makes sense to us.
This will matter in the
second part of the game.
In the second part, you can see that
I'm presented with the description I
provided earlier and the same letters,
but in an order different to how I
saw the letters previously. After
a small delay, all I have to do is
select the same letters as before.
Now
you can see why it's important that the
rules are sensical and meaningful to you.
Because I selected seven
characters based on my rule on
roundedness, I earned seven points.
The more rules you make, the more points
you earn, and the closer you are to being
the top ranked among players from all
around the world. You can make as many
rules as you'd like, as long as you can
think of novel ways to select characters.
So you earn as many points as the number
of characters described by your rule and
the more points you earn across all the
scripts, the more points you win overall.
Glyph features more than 40 different
scripts, allowing players to create
rules for a diverse set of letters.
With this research, we are one step
closer to a visual grammar of letters.
Olivier: Thanks to your participation
we can take the first steps in
describing the building blocks
of the world’s writing systems.